Hello, everybody.
Welcome back to IELTS Intermediate Speaking Course by PREP.
Welcome to Lesson 5.
We are finally tackling the last challenge of the IELTS Speaking Test, Part 3.
To understand how this part works, let's look at three questions, which
represent three different parts of the IELTS Speaking Test.
One, do you prefer studying alone or with a teacher?
Two, describe a teacher who has greatly influenced you.
Three, how has the relationship between teachers and students changed in recent years?
They are all about the same topic, education.
But do you know which part each question belongs to?
Or more importantly, can you see the key difference between them?
Let's learn about how questions in Part 3 are different from the other two in today's lesson.
This lesson aims to help you, one, learn about the format and requirements of IELTS Speaking Part 3.
Two, learn about how to achieve a higher score in this part of the test.
Now let's go.
Now let's look at the first key aspect of Part 3.
Where do Part 3 questions actually come from?
Some of you also might think, surely the examiner just picks some random topics for Part 3.
However, the answer is no.
This is because, in almost every test for Part 3, the examiner
will ask you questions related to the topic you discussed in Part 2.
Yet we will also move away from personal stories of this part
and step into the world of abstract concepts for Part 3.
Let's look at how this transformation happens with real topics.
After you spent two minutes describing a teacher who has greatly influenced
you, then in Part 3, the examiner might ask about the changes
in the relationship between teachers and students in recent years.
Can you notice the pattern?
We will stop saying, my teacher, my school, I think, and start
saying, students today, the education system, society.
This is the shift from the personal to the abstract.
This part is built to test your higher level skills.
The examiner wants to know whether you are able to deal with
unfamiliar topics with greater difficulty, unlike the questions that you face in Part 1 and Part 2.
Because it demands a high level of depth, most candidates agree that
this is the toughest challenge in the entire exam, instead of Part 2.
But with the right structure and test awareness for this part, it
is a hurdle that you definitely can clear to achieve a higher score.
So before we look at specific answer structures, let's systematize the core rules you need to succeed in Part 3.
First, the depth of your response.
You must attempt to extend your responses.
Short answers here will lower your score.
You might ask, why are short answers such a problem here?
The reason is simple.
This section is designed to evaluate your ability to express complex ideas,
justify opinions, or speculate about future trends.
If you give a short and underdeveloped answer, you are showing that you cannot demonstrate these skills.
The examiner is trying to see how much you can explore the
topic, so providing depth is the only way to prove you deserve a high score.
However, please remember that an optimal length for a Part 3 answer is from 30 seconds to a minute.
Longer answers sometimes will lead to grammatical issues or fluency problems,
so remember not to overextend your response.
Second, let's talk about the topics.
You might worry, do I need to be an expert to answer these abstract questions?
The answer is no.
Most Part 3 topics are about universal issues, things that affect everyone's
life like technology, education, or shopping.
They are designed this way so that every candidate, regardless of their job or major, has something to say.
Here, the examiner is testing your ability to share your perspective as a member of society.
Whether you are a high school student or a CEO, you both experience traffic or advertising.
That's why you just need to explain your own view on it.
Remember, most of you cannot know about everything, and also, this part does not aim to test your knowledge.
Finally, it is about interaction between you and your examiner.
The IELTS speaking test is face-to-face, and you have a human examiner who wants to hear you speak.
They will actively encourage you to keep talking and explore the topic.
Because of this, they can also help you if you get stuck.
If they use a difficult word you don't know, do not guess.
The rules allow you to ask for the meaning.
The examiner will explain the term to you.
Doing this ensures you understand the question and keeps your answer on topic.
Don't hesitate to ask for an explanation at any point.
It shows you are engaged in the conversation.
That wraps up our Introduction to IELTS Speaking Part 3, which focuses
on wider topics and more abstract concepts than the previous two parts of the test.
We also established the three golden insights for a high score.
One, the depth of Part 3 response.
You must extend your answers to express complex ideas, but keep them between 30 to 60 seconds.
Two, universal topics.
Remember that you don't need expert knowledge.
You just need to share your perspective on issues that affect society or even your daily life.
Three, interaction.
Don't just answer, engage with the examiner, and don't hesitate to ask for clarification if needed.
Study the lessons, do the exercises regularly, and make the most of yourself study whenever you have some free time.
Till next time, bye!